Ernst Philip Boas Papers 1907-1955 Mss.Ms.Coll.10
American Philosophical Society
- Series III: Works by Boas, 1907-1955
  Typescripts of lectures, addresses, articles, and reviews. Included are lectures at the Central Bureau for Jewish Aged, Inc., and at the Ethical Culture High School; and addresses for the 1910 Ethical Culture High School commencement, the opening of the Amalgamated Laundry Workers Health Center in 1953, and the tenth anniversary of The Physicians Forum, Inc. in 1953. There is also a report on studies that Boas did in 1918 during World War I, "Cases of Effort Syndrome Studied at Camp McClellan, Alabama"; a diary that Boas kept in 1907; and an article entitled "The Responsibility of a Scientist as a Citizen." Works on national health insurance include an untitled article on the American Medical Association and articles entitled "Compulsory Health Insurance in the Framework of a National Health Program" and "National Health Insurance." There are nine scrapbooks containing programs and announcements, reprints, and typescripts of works from 1911 to 1949.
  - Box: A - H (Box 14)
    - "Acutre Coronary Closure", [1925?]
    - "The Aging Process", n.d.
    - Amalgamated Laundry Workers Health Center, Inc.--Address, 20 Jun. 1953
      -See also Ser.I, Amalgamated Laundry Workers Health Center, Inc.
    - [American Medical Association], [194-?]
    - "Aortic Insufficiency", [1927?]
    - "Arcus Senilis and Arteriosclerosis"
    - "Arteriosclerosis and Diabetes"
    - "Arterio-Venous Aneurysm", [1924?]
    - [Atherosclerosis], [1949?]
    - "The Biochemistry of the Ovary, Uterus, and Vagina"
    - "Blood Pressure", [1923?]
    - "Cardiac Disorders Secondary to Disturbances of the Pulmonary Circulation", [1927?]
    - "Cardiovascular Problems After Age 70", n.d.
    - "Care of the Aged", n.d.
    - "Cases of Effort Syndrome Studied at Camp McClellan, Alabama", [1918]
      -See also Ser.I, United States. War Department
    - Central Bureau for Jewish Aged, Inc.--Lecture, 12 Jan. 1950
    - "Chronic Diseases", 1944
    - "The Circulatory Reaction to Exercise", [1927?]
    - "Collection. Illustrating the Classes of Arthropoda and the Orders of Insects", [1911?]
    - "Compulsory Health Insurance in the Framework of a National Health Program", [195-]
    - [Coronary Atherosclerosis], 1954]
    - "Cyanosis", [1923?]
    - Diary, 1907
    - "The Economic Condition of Physicians in New York City"
    - "Edema", [1924?]
    - Ethical Culture High School--Commencement Address, 1910
    - Ethical Culture High School--Lecture, n.d.
    - "Euthanasia", n.d.
    - "Financing Medical Care in the Later Years of Life", 17 Dec. 1953
    - Geriatric Medicine: Medical Care of Later Maturity edited by Edward J. Stieglitz --Review, [1954]
    - [Geriatrics], 1950
    - "Heart Disease Due to Arteriosclerosis of the Coronary Arteries", [1924?]
    - "The Heart in Congenital Syphilis", [1930?]
    - "The Heart in Pregnancy", [1925?]
    - "The Heart in the Tuberculous", [1921]
    - "The Heart in Thyroid Disease", [1931?]
    - "Hypertension", [1924?]
  - Box: I - R (Box 15)
    - "Infection and the Heart"
    - "Last Cholesterol Paper", [1954]
    - "The Magnitude and the Changing Aspect of the Problem of Chronic Disease"
    - "The Medical Care of the Aging Patient", n.d.
    - "Memorandum on the Desirability of Developing Welfare Island for the Care of the Chronic Sick", 19 Oct. 1934
    - "Mitral Stenosis", [1927?]
    - The Nation-- Letter to the Editor, n.d.
    - [National Health Insurance], [195-]
    - "National Health Insurance"--Address at National Health Assembly, [2 May 1948]
    - "Natural History of Heart Disease of Long Duration", 1951
    - "Notes on the Anatomy and Physiology of the Heart"
    - [Osteoarthritis], [194-]
    - "Pathology", [1949?]
    - "Periarteriitis Nodosa", [1924?]
    - The Physicians Forum, Inc. Tenth Anniversary Dinner--Address, 20 Feb. 1953
    - "Pneumopericardium", [1925?]
    - "Preface", n.d.
    - "Preliminary Considerations", n.d.
    - "The Preparedness Agitation"--Letter to the Editor of The New York Evening Post, 1915
    - "The Prevalence of Coronary Artery Disease among Randomly Chosen Men of Italian and Jewish Origin"--with Frederick H. Epstein, 1955
    - "The Probable Effects of Another World War on the Health of the People", 1948
      -See also Ser.II, Conference on Pattern for Survival
    - "Psychoses", [1924?]
    - "Report on the Jewish Home for the Aged", [1944]
    - "The Responsibility of the Scientist as a Citizen", n.d.
    - "Rheumatic Heart Disease", [192-?]
    - [Right Bundle Branch Block]
  - Box: Scrapbook--Bib. #1-3 (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #1, 1911-1923
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #2, 1924-1926
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #3, 1927-1930
  - Box: Scrapbook--Bib. #4-5 (Box 17)
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #4, 1931-1935
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #5, 1936-1939
  - Box: Scrapbook--Bib. #6-7 - Scrapbook--Reprints (Box 18)
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #6, 1940-1944
    - Scrapbook--Bibliography #7, 1947-1949
    - Scrapbook--Reprints, 1944-1946
  - Box: Scrapbook--Speeches (Box 19)
    - Scrapbook--Speeches, 1940-1943
  - Box: St - Y (Box 20)
    - Adlai Stevenson's Presidential Race--Speech on Medical Care, n.d.
    - "Syphilis of the Heart and Aorta"
    - "Traumatic Injuries of the Heart", [1924?]
    - "The Treatment of Coronary Arteriosclerosis", 1954
    - "The Treatment of Heart Failure", n.d.
    - "Tumors", [1926?]
    - "Valvular Lesions", n.d.
    - [Venous Pressure], [1926?]
    - "Vital Capacity", [1924?]
    - "Your Child's Arch-Foe: Rheumatic Fever", n.d.
- Series IV: Works by Others, 1945-1954
  Eleven works, mostly about geriatrics. There are two addresses: Dean A. Clark's 1945 commencement address at the Medical College of Pennsylvania and Alan Gregg's address at the National Health Conference. The works are filed alphabetically by author.
  - Box: C - W (Box 20)
    - Clark, Dean A.
      - "Trends in Medical Practice"-- Commencement Address at Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania, 10 Jan. 1945
    - Crampton, C. Ward
      - "A Proposal for Geriatric Research and Service Stations", 12 Jan. 1948
    - Crampton, C. Ward
      - "Whole Life Records for Whole Life Service"--Lecture, 13 Dec. 1951
    - Epstein, Frederick H.
      -See Ser.III, "The Prevalence of Coronary Artery Disease among Randomly Chosen Men of Italian and Jewish Origin"--with Frederick H. Epstein
      -See Ser. VI, "Relations Between Diet and Atherosclerosis" (with Frederick H. Epstein and R. Simpson)--Review
    - Goldmann, Franz
      - "Medical Care", 1954
    - Gregg, Alan
      - [Address at National Health Conference], n.d.
    - Kaplan
      - "The Care and Treatment of Chronic Cancer Cases"
    - Obrist, Walter D.
      - "The Electroencephalogram of Normal Male Subjects Overs Age Eighty", 1951-1952
    - Shock, N.W. and Marvin J. Yiengst
      - "Basal Metabolism and Basal Respiratory Functions in Aged Males"
    - Shock, N.W.
      - "Physiological Aspects of Aging", [195-]
    - Teleky, Ludwig
      - "Industrial Hygiene in West Germany"
    - White, Marie Angelin
      - "Notes on Sodium Restriction", n.d.
- Series V: Research Notes and Notebooks, 1916-1952
  Bibliographical notes about arteriosclerosis, cholesterol, diabetes, and geriatrics; and research notes about aortic stenosis and pylephlebitis, among other subjects. There are three notebooks: a ward notebook that Boas kept from 1916 to 1917 at The Mount Sinai Hospital; an undated notebook of medical school notes; and a notebook from 1918 labeled "Record of Heart Cases. Ward II." Also in this series are military patient records kept from 1917 to 1918 while Boas was in the United States Army at Camp McClellan, Alabama, as well as general patient records that Boas kept between the 1910s and the 1950s.
  - Box: A - M (Box 21)
    - "Aortic Stenosis", 1952; 2 folders
    - Arteriosclerosis--Bibliographical Notes, [195-]
    - British Health System--Notes, 1950
    - "Calcification of Arteries in Diabetes", [195-]
    - Bibliographical Notes, n.d.
    - [Case Studies], n.d.
    - Cholesterol--Bibliographical Notes, [195-]; 2 folders
    - Diabetes--Bibliographical Notes, [195-]
    - "Digitalis"--Notes, n.d.
    - Geriatrics--Bibliographical Notes, [195-]
    - Heart Rate, [1932]
    - "Hypertension and Chronic Valvular Disease", 1926
    - Medical School Notes, n.d.
    - Miscellaneous Notes, n.d.
    - The Mount Sinai Hospital--Ward Notebook, 1916-1917
  - Box: Patient Records - Patient Records--Military #5 (Box 22)
    - Patient Records
      - Folder #1 A-G, [1910s-1920s]
      - Folder #2 H-P, [1910s-1920s]
      - Folder #3 R-T, [1910s-1920s]
      - Folder #4 U-Z, [1910s-1920s]
    - Patient Records--Military
      - Folder #1 A-Bra, 1917-1918
      - Folder #2 Bri-D, 1917-1918
      - Folder #3 E-Hub, 1917-1918
      - Folder #4 Hul-Le, 1917-1918
      - Folder #5 Li-R, 1917-1918
  - Box: Patient Records--Military #6 - T (Box 23)
    - Patient Records--Military (cont.)
      - Folder #6 S-T, 1917-1918
      - Folder #7 V-W, 1917-1918
    - "Pernicious Anemia", 1926
    - Pylephlebitis, n.d.
    - "Record of Heart Cases. Ward II"--Notebook, 1918
    - "Treatment of Diabetes", n.d.
- Series VI: Materials Gathered After Ernst P. Boas's Death, 1955-1980
  Materials that were collected and compiled by Norman F. Boas after his father's death in 1955. These materials include obituaries; condolence letters sent to Boas's family after his death; information about Boas's cardiotachometer; correspondence and a card file documenting the donation by Norman F. Boas of his father's library to various repositories; and letters written about Ernst P. Boas for the memorial meeting held in his honor on 19 April 1955. The authors of these letters have been cross-referenced in Series I. This series also includes a volume (edited by Romana Javitz in 1960) of excerpts from Ernst P. Boas's letters; many of the originals are held by the American Philosophical Society Library. There is a separate folder of transcriptions of Ernst P. Boas's letters from 1907-1935 and translations from the German. Many of these letters are to his father, Franz Boas. This material has been photocopied and annotated with the appropriate American Philosophical Society Library call numbers.
  - Box: B - Le (Box 23)
    - Biographical Material, 1955-1956
    - The Ernst P. Boas Memorial Fund, 1955-1962, n.d.
    - Cardiotachometer, 1957-1975
    - Condolence Letters on Ernst P. Boas's Death, 1955
      - Folder #1 A-K
      - Folder #2 L-Z
    - Finison, Lorenz J., 1976
    - Letters of Ernst P. Boas, M.D., 1905-1953, edited by Romana Javitz, 4 Feb. 1960
      - Folder #1
    - Letters of Ernst P. Boas, M.D., 1907-1935--Translations and Transcriptions
      - Folder #2
  - Box: Li - R (Box 24)
    - Library--Ernst P. Boas
      -See also Ser.VI, Cardfile. Library--Ernst P. Boas
      - Folder #1, 1956-1975
      - Folder #2, 1957-1980
    - Loewi, Otto, 1961
      -See also Ser.I, Loewi, Otto
    - Memorial Meeting for Ernst P. Boas, 19 Apr. 1955
      - Binger, Carl
      - Black, Algernon D.
      - Cobb, W. Montague
      - Cohn, Alfred E.
      - Davis, Michael M.
      - Deutsch, Albert
      - Dublin, Louis I.
      - Frothingham, Channing
      - Goldmann, Franz
      - Laurence, William L.
      - Levin, Morton L.
      - Levine, Samuel A.
      - Peters, John P.
      - Roemer, Milton I.
      - Salk, Jonas E.
      - Wagner, Robert F.
    - National Committee for Resettlement of Foreign Physicians, Inc., 1955, 1957
    - The Physicians Forum, Inc., 1955
    - "Relations Between Diet and Atherosclerosis" (with Frederick H. Epstein and R. Simpson)--Review, 1956
  - Box: Cardfile, Library--Ernst P. Boas (Box 25)
- Series VII: Photographs, 1917-1953
  Scientific photographs, as well as portrait photographs. Those of a scientific nature include the subjects of aneurysm, blood pressure, Boas's cardiotachometer, coronary damage, endocarditis, and myocardial degeneration. There are also photographs used in Boas's article, "Calcification in the Pineal Gland" and electrocardiograms, done from 1917 to 1952, presumably by Boas. The portrait photographs are of Boas from the 1920s to the 1950s, and also show him in group shots with the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University, at the Sidney Hillman Health Center, at the Montefiore Hospital for Chronic Diseases, and at the Kecoughton Conference.
  - Box: A - M (Box 26)
    - "Aneurysm", n.d.
    - "Blood Pressure", n.d.
    - Boas, Ernst P.
      -See Ser. VII, [Columbia University. College of Physicians and Surgeons--Group Shot]
      -See Ser. VII, Epstein, Fred and Ernst P. Boas at Sidney Hillman Health Center
      -See Ser. VII, Montefiore Hospital for Chronic Diseases--Group Shot
    - Boas, Ernst P., 1953
    - Boas, Ernst P. Boas--At Table, [194-?]
    - Boas, Ernst P. Boas--Full-Sized Proofs
      - Folder #1, [1920s-1930s?]
      - Folder #2, [1920s-1930s?]
      - Folder #3, [1920s-1930s?]
      - Folder #4, [193-?]
      - Folder #5, [194-?]
      - Folder #6, [195-?]
      - Folder #7, [195-?]
    - Boas, Ernst P.--Giving Speech
      - Folder #1, [192-?]
      - Folder #2, 29 Jun. 1950
    - Boas, Ernst P.--In Group Shot at Kecoughton Conference, [Sep. 1952]
      -See also Ser.II, Programs
    - Boas, Ernst P.--In Philadelphia, [194-?]
    - Boas, Ernst P., Harry Hopkins, and Dr. Wyckoff, 1930-1932
    - "Calcification in the Pineal Gland", 1918
    - "Calcification of Arteries", n.d.
    - Cardiotachometer, 1927
    - [Columbia University. College of Physicians and Surgeons--Group Shot], [191-?]
      - Boas, Ernst P.
    - [Coronary Damage], n.d.
    - Electrocardiograms
      -See also Ser. V, Patient Records, #3
      - Folder #1, [192-]
      - Folder #2, [192-]
      - Folder #3, 1952
      - Folder #4, 1952
    - Electrocardiograms Done at Rockefeller Institute, 1917
    - "Endocarditis"
    - Epstein, Fred and Ernst P. Boas at Sidney Hillman Health Center, 1951-1952
    - Hopkins, Harry
      -See Ser. VII, Boas, Ernst P., Harry Hopkins, and Dr. Wyckoff
    - "Lung-Thickened Vessels from Passive Congestion", n.d.
    - "Metastasis in Heart", n.d.
    - Michelson, Nicholas
    - "Mitral Stenosis", n.d.
    - Montefiore Hospital for Chronic Diseases--Group Shot, [192-?]
      - Boas, Ernst P.
      - Michelson, Nicholas
    - "Myocardial Degeneration", n.d.
- Oversized - Series II, VII (Oversize 1)
  - Series II, Subject Files
    - The American Board of Internal Medicine--Certificate, 1 Jul. 1937
    - Collection of Plant Specimens, 1911
    - Columbia University--Diploma (B.S.), 1910 June 1
    - Columbia University--Diploma (M.A.), 1912
    - Columbia University--Diploma (M.D.), 1914 Juen 3
    - Ethical Culture School--Diploma, 1903 June 1
    - Ethical Culture School--Diploma, 1907 May 29
    - Health Insurance (National), 1944
    - Medical Society of the County of New York--Membership Certificate, 1917 Dec. 21
    - The Mount Sinai Hospital--Certificate, 1916 Dec. 31
    - National Committee for the Resettlement of Foreign Physicians
      -See Oversized, New York Association for New Americans
    - The New York Academy of Medicine--Membership Certificate, 1921 Feb. 3
    - New York Association for New Americans -- Certificate, 1950 Nov. 2
    - New York World's Fair. Advisory Committee on Medicine and Public Health--Certificate, 1939
    - Pi Gamma Mu Honor Society--Membership Certificate, 1928 Nov. 10
    - United States Army--Certificate of Appointment as First Lieutenant in the Medical Section of the Officers' Reserve Corps, 1917 Aug. 6
    - United States Army--Certificate of Appointment as Captain in the Medical Section of the Officers' Reserve Corps, 1918 Apr. 20
    - University of the State of New York--License to practice medicine, 1914 June 26
  - Ser. VII, Photographs
    - Boas, Ernst P., 1953